<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Justice of the Parliament, in inflicting of punishments subsequent to offences, vindicated and the lawfulness of the present government asserted : with some animadversions upon the second vindication of the magistracy and government of England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3651</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15074</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12255685</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12255685</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57428</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57428)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 899:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Justice of the Parliament, in inflicting of punishments subsequent to offences, vindicated and the lawfulness of the present government asserted : with some animadversions upon the second vindication of the magistracy and government of England.</title>
                  <author>Shower, Bartholomew, Sir, 1658-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Wing attributes authorship to Sir Bartholomew Shower; others follow the Brit. Mus. in entering it anonymously. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Punishment --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57428:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57428:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE JUSTICE OF THE Parliament, In Inflicting of PUNISHMENTS Subſequent to OFFENCES, VINDICATED. And the Lawfulneſs of the Preſent Government ASSERTED.</p>
            <p>With ſome ANIMADVERSIONS upon the <hi>Second Vindication of the Magiſtracy and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Black Bull</hi> in the <hi>Old Baily.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:57428:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57428:2"/>
            <head>THE JUSTICE of the PARLIAMENT, In Inflicting of PUNISHMENTS Subſequent to OFFENCES, VINDICATED, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. I Hapned two days ſince to meet a Sheet called, <hi>A Second Vindication of the Magiſtracy and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of</hi> England; and upon peruſal, found it to be a weak Effort to juſtifie what had been before writ in the behalf of the Government and its Miniſters, for the Condemnation and Execution of my Lord <hi>Ruſſel.</hi> It does particularly take notice of a Half ſheet entituled, <hi>A Juſtification of the Act which reverſes that Noble Lord's Attainder;</hi> And I muſt needs own, that if impudent, downright Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Law and Facts, paſſes for Argument and Proof, he has effectually performed what he arrogantly undertakes, which is, the refuting the Reaſons and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of that and the other more Learned late Prints
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57428:3"/>which have been publiſhed to do Right to the Name and Memory of a Perſon, whoſe Character is very well deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by one of thoſe worthy Gentlemen, who atteſted in his Favour at his Trial, <hi>That he was one of the best Sons, one of the beſt Fathers, and one of the beſt Maſters, one of the beſt Husbands, one of the beſt Friends, and one of the beſt Chriſtians we had.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. I ſhall not preſume to obtrude a Defence in the behalf of Sir <hi>R. A.</hi> and Mr. <hi>H.</hi> I ſhall not do them ſo much Injuſtice, as to impoſe on them ſo ill ad Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate: And therefore the Province I do aſſign my ſelf principally is, to expoſe the Weakneſs and Fallacies of that Part of the Sheet which relates to the Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſhall not meddle with the reſt, farther than is neceſſary to make good the Authorities and Poſitions from which the Juſtifier infers that Noble Lord was ſo far from being guilty of a Legal Treaſon, that the Kings Judges and Counſel (in ſubſerviency to a Predeſtination of the State, for removing him right or wrong out of the way) were forced to call ſuch Vertues Treaſon, as in a more juſt and grateful Age would have deſerved Statues, Triumphs, and other Demonſtrations of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, paid by the <hi>Romans</hi> and other Nations to their Patriots, and the Aſſertors of the Liberties of their Country.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Our Author obſerves, (<hi>pag.</hi> 2.) <hi>That Sir</hi> R. A. <hi>calls the Sentence and Execution a Murder; and if ſo, he is ſure that he is bound in Conſcience to proſecute an Indictment againſt the Judges, Recorder, the Grand and Petit Jury, &amp;c.</hi> But he concludes, <hi>that nene of theſe ſhew any fear of it.</hi> The Juſtifier, and all that have writ on the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, did alſo in effect, tho' not perhaps in expreſs Terms, concur in that Opinion; and for my part, I do not ſee how it can deſerve a more ſoft and gentle Appellation. Our Author ſays indeed, <hi>The Perſons that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57428:3"/>were concerned in it, are as ſafe as under an Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity.</hi> My Temper and Diſpoſition always inclines me to Mercy; and tho' I muſt allow in the Speculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Executing of Juſtice upon Offenders is as great a Duty as ſhewing them Mercy; yet I find a very great difference in the Practice; the Exerciſe of Acts of Mercy being much more pleaſing and agreeable than of Juſtice. But if I had the Honour of being a Member of Parliament, I ſhould think that this natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Tendency of my Mind ought not to make me for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, that Acts of Indempnity, and all Humane Laws and Sanctions, muſt be conſiſtent with the Statutes and Ordinances of God himſelf; and where he in his Sacred Word has been pleaſed to declare himſelf, in ſuch Caſes neither the Parliament, nor any other Political Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, can exert its Authority. There muſt therefore be ſome Account taken for the innocent Blood that has been ſpilt in this Kingdom of late Years.</p>
            <p>There neither is, nor ever was, any Municipal Law in the World more careful to preſerve the Lives of the Subject, than the Law of <hi>England;</hi> but 'tis not to be denied, that this Law hath ſuffered extremely in its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation both at home and abroad, and particularly in that excellent Part of it, Trials by Juries, becauſe it hath been the Inſtrument and Property (tho' a forced and unwilling one) of its own and the Churches Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to take away the Lives of this Noble Lord, and others, who they thought willing or able to obſtruct or diſappoint their Deſigns of introducing Popery and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny. And ſhall there be nothing done to vindicate the Reputation of our Law, and to make it appear to the World, that the Fault was not in the Law it ſelf, but in thoſe wicked and corrupt Miniſters and Judges who had the diſtribution of it?</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:57428:4"/>
            <p>The Occaſion and Inducement of the Statute of 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. was, that corrupt Judges did adjudge Crimes Treaſon, that were not really ſo great: But our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Judges have exalted themſelves beyond thoſe; they have condemned a Man of Treaſon, that was not only innocent of the Crime, but was eminent for his Vertues, and indeed for no other Crime than diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging his Duty: For I do conceive, that 'tis a Duty incumbent upon every Subject, to ſupport and defend the Government he lives under, and to oppoſe all Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Steps towards the Change and Alteration of it, that have not the Concurrence of the Legiſlative Authority.</p>
            <p>I think this Propoſition will be allowed as a Principle, and then I am ſure my Lord <hi>R.</hi> is to be both juſtified and applauded for all that he tranſacted: For, what other Charge was he guilty of than this? King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second (who was a Concealed Papiſt, and by ſo much the more Dangerous) had, in conjunction with His Brother, (who was an Owned one, and by ſo much the more Generous) formed a Project to extirpate the Proteſtant Religion, and eſtabliſh their own in theſe Kingdoms; and, as previous and neceſſary thereto, there was a neceſſity to deſtroy the Laws, and to change the whole Frame of the Government; for both, as they then ſtood, and were conſtituted, were ſuch a ſtrong Guard and Defence to the Proteſtant Religion, and were ſo particularly calculated againſt the return of Popery, that it was in vain to attempt any thing, either to the prejudice of the one, or in favour of the other, ſo long as the Laws and the Government continued.</p>
            <p>Tho' there were formerly (I know) ſeveral good Proteſtants that were incredulous of this Deſign; yet the Tranſactions of the State after, and that King's owning himſelf a Romaniſt at his Death, has abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57428:4"/>ſatisfied all unprejudiced Men of the Truth of it ſince. My Lord <hi>R.</hi> was one of thoſe that had ſo early and ſo large a Proſpect in this Matter, that his Reaſon fully convinced him at that time of what every one has been ſince convinced of. Then the Treaſon of my Lord <hi>R.</hi> reſolves into this; That he being upon good and rational Grounds, determined in the belief that King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second and the Duke of <hi>Y.</hi> had conſpired to aboliſh the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to ſubvert the Laws and the Government; and obſerving the Counſels, Meaſures, and all the Proceedings of the Court to be correſpondent to that End, and to have a direct and natural tendency towards it; He did joyn with one <hi>Judas,</hi> but with divers other Great and Worthy Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, to conſider how to preſerve our Religion, our Government, and our Laws, in that time of danger and diſtreſs: For before the date of any of the pretended Treaſonable Practices objected to him, it ought to be remembred, 1. That the Fountain of all our Laws and Liberties, our High Court of Parliament, was polluted by Court-bribery and Subornation. 2. That it had been frequently and abruptly broke up and diſſolved, before it could perform any of the Truſts or Duties it owed to the Country. 3. That there was an infamous Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ordered to be read in all Churches, ſolemnly, in the time of Divine Service, againſt the Proceedings of the Houſe of Commons; which could have no other aim, than to render that part of the Conſtitution obnoxious to the People, and to make them believe it was become impracticable, and unſafe for the Government to aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them. 4. That there was a mortal Wound given to the Privilege and Rights of Parliament, by the Trial of <hi>Fitzhrrris</hi> in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> being under an Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by the Encouragement and Welcome given to the Addreſſes and Abhorrences of the <hi>Mobile,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting a Condemnation of Parliamentary Proceedings. 5. That there had been Witneſſes tampered with, if
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57428:5"/>not actually ſuborned, to ſwear divers Noblemen and Gentlemen out of their Lives. 6. That there was a bold and open Incroachment on the Charter and Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes of the City of <hi>London,</hi> which uſher'd in that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Deſolation which ſucceeded on all the Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>England.</hi> The extorting the Charters from all Cities and Burroughs by <hi>Quo Warranto's,</hi> and involuntary Surrenders (which divers were forced to make to ſave their Lands and their Charitable Donations, which they were threatned ſhould be otherwiſe ſeiſed) did effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally encompaſs the Deſign of overturning the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For all Writers in Politicks do agree in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, That when the Legiſlative Power is removed, or altered from that Place, State, or Poſition in which it was ſetled upon the Original Conſtitution, that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is diſſolved: And I think it very clear, that by the Deſtructions of the old Charters, and the Eſtabliſhment of our Cities and Burroughs under the new, the King had in effect uſurped the whole Legiſlative Authority: For he had before a Power over two Parts of it, which were Himſelf and the Houſe of Lords; becauſe he could prefer what Number he pleaſed of his own Creatures to be Members of that Houſe, who ſhould vote as He ſhould order and direct; and he had now got the Houſe of Commons under his Girdle, by the Powers he reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the New Charters, to model and change the Magiſtracy, and the Officers who had the Conduct of the Elections, and the right of returning the Perſons E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. In theſe violations of our civil Rights, ſome Perſons (as I have the Charity to believe) did ingage and concur through Inadvertency, not ſeeing through that Scheme which had been concerted between the two Brothers, for the bringing about their deſign, and theſe withdrawing from their Counſels when it appeared bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced; and their being ſo inſtrumental and aſſiſting to the late Revolution, and the ſetling us in our preſent Condition of Happineſs, ſeems to Attone for paſt Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57428:5"/>7. It muſt not be forgot, that originally in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Priviledges of the Subject were greater, and the Prerogatives of the Crown not ſo large as in <hi>England,</hi> and yet there the old Conſtitution was ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed, that there hardly remained the Ruines of the ancient Government; but it might be ſaid <hi>jam ſeges ubi Troja fuit,</hi> and there was (avowedly) exerciſed an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary and Deſpotick Juriſdiction. The Duty and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligation of the King was as great to govern the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Scotland</hi> according to their Laws, as to govern us according to our Law; and therefore we might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude we ſhould receive the ſame fate and the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Juſtice, whenever the King ſhould think it as ſafe and as feaſible. There were theſe and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther palpable ſteps and advantages towards Popery and Arbitrary Power, antecedent to any of the Facts charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on my Lord <hi>Ruſſell:</hi> And was it not every <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man's Duty as well as Intereſt, to endeavour a ſtop to the Courſe of thoſe Counſels, which were ſo directly aimed and levelled at our Church and Government? And was there the leaſt Proof that my Lord <hi>Ruſſell</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or Privity extended any further?</p>
            <p n="4">IV. In Page 3. He beſtows large Commendations on the Perſon that was the Kings Sollicitor at that time, and excuſes the Council, by ſaying, <hi>That every Advocate is to do his utmoſt, and a failure had deſerved the worſt of Names, &amp;c.</hi> I do acknowledg that in all times Lawyers have allowed themſelves too great a Latitude, when they Act meerly as Council, and 'tis an Opinion that has obtained among us, That we ought not judicially to be called to an Account for any thing we offer or preſs in favour of our Clyent, or againſt his Adveſary, ſo we have it in our Inſtructions; and though I muſt always have a deference to the Memory of my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> and muſt own my Obligations to his Learned and Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Works, yet I cannot without the higheſt degree of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57428:6"/>Indignation, conſider his Conduct when he was Attorney General againſt Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh</hi> in his Tryal; nor can I forgive my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> for his vehement and partial ſtreining of Law and Fact againſt his Patron and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> in his firſt Tryal upon the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles exhibited againſt him for miſcarriages in <hi>Ireland.</hi> But let it not paſs for Authentick Doctrine, That a Council is a Criminal, or that he does not perform his Duty if he does not impoſe falſe Law upon the Court, and falſe Facts, and falſe Conſequences deduced from the Facts upon the Jury, which was plainly done in the Caſe of my Lord <hi>Ruſſell,</hi> as has been already, and ſhall be in this again further evinced. As to the then Sollicitor's Character, if his Actings as Counſel againſt this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lord, and ſome other Perſons, be put in a Parentheſis, 'tis as great as any Man of the Profeſſion of the Law; but if he were my Father, I muſt condemn his Deportment in thoſe Caſes, and ſome others whilſt he was Sollicitor to the two laſt Kings.</p>
            <p n="5">V. In the ſame Page, our Author ſays, <q>
                  <hi>That the World gueſſes that he who wrote the Reply</hi> (viz. <hi>Sir</hi> R. A.) <hi>did write the half Sheet, called the Juſtification, and ſays 'tis really ſportive to read the Juſtifier, commending the Defender and Replyant doing the ſame good Office for the Juſtifier; and that he ſpends a whole Page in the moſt fulſome Praiſes on that ſmall bulk Author, and rejoyces that the Work was done to his hand, which is a very pretty Jeſt. It is at most but</hi> R. <hi>for</hi> A. <hi>and</hi> A. <hi>for</hi> R. <hi>and</hi> R. A. <hi>ſtill, which is much better than the contrary Practice, of which ſome Authors have been guilty.</hi>
               </q> 1. The World he here means is (I dare ſay) his own ſelf, ſince none elſe can have ſo weak a Judgment, as ſo far to wrong the Defender, by ſuſpecting him to write ſo ſimple a thing; and I aſſure our Author, if I had not a very mean Opinion of his Underſtanding, the Juſtifier would value himſelf extreamly upon the miſtake. 2. The
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57428:6"/>Juſtifier owns the Defender to have diſparaged his Judgment, in the Praiſes he has beſtowed upon him, to which he was led by his Zeal and Affection to the ſubject Matter the Juſtifier writ upon; the Juſtifier diſclaims all Title and Merit to any other Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation than this, That he writ upon no other Principle hope, or inducement, than the doing right to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory and Reputation of the Noble Lord who is dead, to his Lady, Children, and other Relations who are living; and to the Publick Juſtice and Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which were violently wreſted to give a Sanction to his Condemnation, that we may reaſonably pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume was firſt reſolved upon, before the Crime was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered or concerted that he ſhould be Condemned for. 3. He might have ſpared his Reflection on the ſmall bulk Author, ſince he was induſtriouſly ſo for the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons therein mentioned, it being hinted, that it was deſign'd only for the ſatisfaction of ſuch as had not the opportunity, or wanted leiſure to peruſe the greater and more deſerving Works upon the ſame Subject. 4. In the next Print 'tis deſired our Author will be pleaſed to explain his laſt Period recited in this Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz. It is at moſt but</hi> R. <hi>for</hi> A. <hi>and</hi> A. <hi>for</hi> R. <hi>and</hi> R. A. <hi>ſtill, which is much better than the contrary Practice, of which ſome Authors have been guilty.</hi> I underſtand what is intended by the Capital Letters, but for my Soul I cannot find out the <hi>Antecedent</hi> to the <hi>Relative It;</hi> or if <hi>It</hi> be a Mark of imperſonally, I am at a loſs for the <hi>Antecedent</hi> to the firſt <hi>Relative Which;</hi> and I am at a loſs to know what Practice it is that ſome Authors are guilty of contrary to the Practice of <hi>R. A.</hi> At preſent all this is unintelligible, and therefore the Author muſt pardon me if (until his Clavis or Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary comes out) I put this Sentence under Title <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> in my common Place.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:57428:7"/>
            <p n="6">VI. In Page 4. He ſays, <hi>The Author of the Remarks quarrels with the legality of the Jurors, the Defender with that of the Indictments, and both with the Evidence. The Author of the Sheet differs from them in the two firſt, but agrees with them in the laſt.</hi> The Author of the half Sheet, called the Juſtification (which I ſuppoſe he means by the Author of the Sheet) is ſo far from differing from them in the two firſt, that he does think the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment faulty, and not ſo certain as it ought to be; but he conceives the Objections to the Jurors and to the Evidence are never to be got over. Indeed the Juſtifier takes no notice of the defects of the Indictment nor of the Jury; not only becauſe he could add nothing on thoſe Heads to what had been obſerved before, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe becauſe it was not ſo pertinent to his purpoſe, which was to frame and digeſt the Caſe of my Lord <hi>Ruſſell</hi> into ſuch a plain, ſhort, and eaſie Method, that no Perſon might want Leiſure to read, or Capacity to underſtand it: And therefore where he was obliged to uſe our legal Terms and Ideoms, he was very careful <hi>to add an Explanation to them.</hi> To underſtand the Force and Validity of the Objections to the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to the Jury, there was required conſiderable Skill in Law and the Rules of Pleading; and the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier did not preſume to be able to inſtruct any one ſo qualified; but there is no Woman wants Logick to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that my Lord <hi>Ruſſell</hi> was innocent, if it be true, as the Juſtifier affirmed, and proved by quoting his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, <hi>That his Sentence was againſt the expreſs and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Opinion of the two greateſt Men of the Law, the Lord</hi> Coke <hi>and</hi> Hales; <hi>againſt the Opinion of ſeveral Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; againſt a general and certain Maxime of the Law, and againſt the Firſt and Original end of making any Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute concerning Treaſons.</hi> I ſay there could be none of ſo ſmall an Underſtanding, but muſt upon the reading, determine either, That the Judgment againſt my Lord <hi>Ruſſell</hi> was Illegal and Arbitrary, or that the Juſtifier
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57428:7"/>was diſingenious, in impoſing upon the People falſe Quotations and Authorities, which even our Author has not the brow to charge him with, though he does endeavour to avoid the force of them by ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, as ſhall be conſidered in their proper Place. Our Author therefore has given us a great Inſtance, either of his Candor or his Sence, by inferring that the Juſtifier differs in his Opinion from the two Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gentlemen abovementioned, as to the Indictment and Jury, becauſe he was filent, and delivered no Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion at all one way or other.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. In Page 5. He ſays, <hi>That the Replyant refers his Reader to the Juſtification, and therefore let's examine that a little; a third part of it is ſpent upon the Evidence, but that is not within my Province,</hi> &amp;c. 1. He is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly miſtaken in his Computation, for there is not a tenth part of it ſpent upon the Evidence: The Juſtifier did, and does conceive the Evidence in reſpect of the Character of the Witneſſes in general, the particular Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they were under, and of the ſubject Matter which they did Depoſe, to be ſo defective, and ſo far from maintaining the Charge of the Indictment, that he took it for granted, that there was none ſo hardy as to defend it. 2. But our Author did not conſider well, when he ſaid that the Evidence was not within his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince; for the Province he has undertaken, is to Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Government in its Proceedings againſt my Lord <hi>Ruſſell;</hi> and if the Government be ſuſpected and charged, for giving aſſurance to Priſoners, that they ſhould be Pardoned or Hanged according as they Swore Matter to Convict or Acquit this Noble Lord and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and for refuſing to grant Pardons, until the Terms and Conditions of obtaining the ſame were actually performed, by ſwearing this Lord out of his Life to ſave their own; I ſay, if the Government be charged for uſing theſe and other indirect Courſes, to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57428:8"/>procure Evidence againſt him and others, (as it really is from the Mouth of one, if not more, of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes themſelves) then the Government wants Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in that Particular, and conſequently the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is as much within his Province as the Indictment and Judgment; and as the Actings of the Judges and Counſel, which in another place he owns to be his Province to defend and juſtifie. I deſire our Author hereafter, to poſtpone the giving his Works a Title till he has finiſhed them; for the Contradiction and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity between the Title and Body of his Sheet is really a very great ſcandal and reproach to him.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. In the ſame Page he goes on thus: <hi>As to the reſt, the force of it, if any ſeems to be founded on his firſt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, the Conſpiring to do a thing is not the doing a thing, and he quotes two great Mens Names for it, I would have agreed that, though he had ſpared the Authority to juſtifie it, but this is ſufficiently anſwered in the Sheet.</hi> 1. Our Author now gives us an inſtance of his Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as he has done before ſeveral times of his Judgment; I deſire him to point at that part of the <hi>Juſtification,</hi> out of which he quotes that abſurd and ridiculous Aſſertion, <hi>That the Conſpiring to do a thing is not the doing a thing.</hi> I ſhould never have been able to gueſs what he meant, if he had not added the Quotation of the two great Mens Names; the two great Men are the Lords <hi>Coke</hi> and <hi>Hales,</hi> which the Juſtifier cites to prove, <hi>That Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring to Levy War is not Treaſon, nor an Overt Act to prove the Intention or compaſſing of the King's death.</hi> The Juſtifier uſes their own Words, and tells his Reader ſo; and is not our Author a Man of a ſtrange Forehead, to Conſtrue Poſitions laid down by <hi>Coke</hi> and <hi>Hales</hi> ſo abſurdly? 2. If the Propoſition, <hi>Conſpiring to Levy War is not Treaſon,</hi> be to be <hi>expounded,</hi> (as our Author does) <hi>That Conſpiring to do a thing is not doing the thing,</hi> what becomes of our Judges, who have adjudged, <hi>That the Conſpiring to do a thing was the doing a thing?</hi> for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57428:8"/>they adjudged to Levy War, Treaſon, within the intent of Stat. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. tho it be not in the Letter. Our Author one might think play'd Booty; for tho he aſſumes the Stile of the Judges Vindicator; yet he loads them with a more groſs and ſtupid Imputation, than either the Defence, Remarks, or Juſtification; but I'le be his Compurgator, I believe him true and faithful to his Truſt, this was a Blunder, and Blunders we find to flow from him, with a wonderful and natural Facility; and we may obſerve one more in this period, where be ſays, <hi>This is ſufficiently an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in the Sheet:</hi> Now, tho I never ſaw that Sheet (he muſt mean his firſt Sheet) till lately; yet, I am aſſured it was printed before the Juſtification came out, and then I deſire to know, how he comes to Anſwer a Paper he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw, nor knew to be in being; there muſt be Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy or Revelation in the Caſe, that is certain; but admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting he had ſaid, That what was writ in the Sheet, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſute this part of the <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and ſo rendred an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer now unneceſſary, which was his intent, if he had any at all, I ſay, That to a general Affirmative, I can but op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a general Negative, that 'tis not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I confeſs I might have ſpared my Criticiſm on the Incorrectneſs of our Authors Expreſſions, ſince there are ſo many more important Faults and Errors, to entertain me with.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. In the ſame page, <hi>He ſays, that the Juſtifier offers an Argument from the late Statutes declaring Treaſons; becauſe they were Temporary; but I anſwer as the Sheet doth, they were in affirmance of the Old Law; and I can ſhew him three or four Temporary, and an hundred other Acts of Parliament that are ſo, and therefore that is no Argument at all; but I am, as the Party I juſtify was, confined to a Sheet, and therefore cannot enlarge.</hi> 1. The Temporary Statutes for making a bare Conſpiracy to levy War, Treaſon, were one of the Topicks from which the Juſtifier drew his Arguments to prove that it was not Treaſon within the intent of the Statute of <hi>E.</hi> 3. upon which my Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi> was indicted; for he did, and does ſtill think, that ſo many Parliaments would not have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57428:9"/>troubled themſelves to make ſpecial Statutes concerning it, if they had thought it Treaſon by any Statute before in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and did alſo infer, that all thoſe Parliaments did not judge it fit to be a continued ſtanding Treaſon, becauſe then they would have made their Statutes perpetual, and not remporary. When there were Jealouſies and Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of an Invaſion from a Foreign Enemy, and of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects holding a correſpondency with him, as in Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> and other Reigns; upon ſuch, and the like Emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, the Wiſdom of the Parliament did think fitting to make a Conſpiracy to levy War Treaſon; and there is no doubt but ſuch an Act would be at this time ſeaſonable. 2. His bare and confident averment that they were in affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Old Law, and that he can ſhew three or four Temperary Statutes that are ſo, muſt not bear down thoſe ſtrong Reaſons which induce me to believe that they were introductive of New Law; I believe he may be ſo learned as to produce a great many other Acts, that are only decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory of the Old Law; but I'm ſure 'tis not common nor uſual to make temporary Acts in affirmance of perpetual Acts of Parliament, which is the Point in queſtion: For if our Author means any thing that is pertinent, 'tis that theſe temporary Acts are in affirmance of the Statute of <hi>E.</hi> 3. which is perpetual. 'Tis true, the temporary Statute of 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. (as our Author cites) does enact, That if any perſon or perſons whatſoever ſhall, within the Realm, or without, compaſs or imagine the Death of the King, <hi>&amp;c. and ſuch Compaſſings, Imaginations,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall expreſs, utter, or declare, by any Printing, Writing, Preaching, or malicious-adviſed Speaking, being legally convicted thereof by,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then every ſuch,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall,</hi> &amp;c. But no man (except our Author) would ſay that this is in affirmance of Stat. <hi>E.</hi> 3. as to the compaſſing the King's Death. The Statute of <hi>E.</hi> 3. does provide, That there muſt be ſome Overt-act; but it does not determine what ſhall be a good and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Overt-act to prove the Compaſſing: If the matter be clear, it leaves it to the Judges; if there be any doubt or difficulty, then it does expreſly direct the Judges to reſpit
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57428:9"/>their Judgments till the meeting of the Parliament, that the Caſe may be reſolved there. But the Statute 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. declares the compaſſing the King's Death, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the expreſſing the ſame <hi>by any Printing, Writing, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or malicious-adviſed Speaking, to be Treaſon,</hi> the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulative <hi>And</hi> makes it clear, that the principal End of this part of the Statute was to particulariſe and aſcertain, That ſuch Facts therein mentioned ſhould be ſufficient Overt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acts of the compaſſing during King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Life, that were not ſo by the Statute of <hi>E.</hi> 3. which left it general, and at large. Is not our Author a man of an excellent Head, to apprehend this <hi>to be only a Confirmation of the Old Statute in words at length?</hi> Indeed he does ſay, <hi>That it was agreed to be ſo in the Houſe of Commons,</hi> 1 Jac. 2. <hi>and when a Motion was made to renew that Law, the Lawyers, anſwer was, That the</hi> 25 E. 3. <hi>did the ſame thing.</hi> I have enquired of ſome diligent and obſerving Members of that Parliament concerning the truth of this Allegation, and they aſſure me there was no ſuch Anſwer made by the Lawyers, nor no ſuch thing agreed by the Houſe; but they give me this Account of the matter: There was a Bill brought in to renew the Statute of 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. and upon the ſecond or third reading, it was moved by Mr. <hi>Tipping</hi> ('tis for his Credit to be named), That there might be an explanatory Proviſo, <hi>That Preaching, Writing, or Speaking against</hi> Popery, <hi>and against the Doctrines and Principles of the</hi> Church of Rome, <hi>ſhould not be conſtrued or intended within the intent of the Act.</hi> This was thought ſo reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, that it was immediately agreed unto, and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee appointed preſently to withdraw into the Speaker's Chamber, to pen the Proviſo, and the Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph</hi> came there to be aſſiſting in it. Upon this, the Bill was dropt and let fall, and no man ever after preſſed it further; which may give all men ſatisfaction what uſe was at that time deſigned to be made of it; and that all our Learned Clergy who did ſince Preach and Write againſt Popery, would have been in danger (if the Bill had paſſed) to have been conſtrued into a Treaſon, Praemunire, or ſome
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57428:10"/>other great Penalty within the intent of that Bill, to the ruine of Them and their Families. This was in King <hi>James</hi>'s firſt Parliament, when we had the moſt ſimple, plain, and ſolemn Aſſurances of Protecting our Religion and our Laws, that was poſſible to be deviſed. It does now ſufficiently appear how inſufficiently our Author has anſwered this Argument of the Juſtifier: 'Tis true, he does make an Apology (and a very pretty one it is), <hi>That he is confined to a Sheet, and therefore cannot enlarge.</hi> He ſays, when he comes to anſwer Mr. <hi>H. That he wants time.</hi> But I deſire to know, How it comes that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpare time, or that he is limited to a Sheet? Who is it that does ſet theſe bounds unto his Writings? It were to be wiſhed, That the perſon who has ſo great Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over him as to confine him to a Sheet, would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it a little further, and engage him not to write at all. If it had been a year ago, I ſhould have preſumed he were thus ſtreightned from the attendance he owed to ſome great Place; for I believe truly, his Parts, Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Integrity, and other Qualifications, could not fail of recommending him to an Eminent Office (perhaps <hi>a Recorder of a Great City,</hi> or the like) in the late Reign. The Reader may obſerve what ſort of man he is, who when he is gravell'd, and can offer nothing of Reaſon, is forced to have recourſe to ſo poor and pitiful a ſhift, as to pretend he wants time, or that he is confined to a Sheet, which bears the Price of four Sheets; and, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the value of if, he might have afforded more of them for our Money.</p>
            <p n="10">X. In the ſame Page he obſerves, <hi>That the</hi> Juſtifier <hi>lays down a Rule for Conſtruction of Statutes, That a thing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularis'd in one part, is not to be conſtrued within the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral words of another part; but that Rule has near four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Exceptions in the Books: Beſides, it comes not to this Caſe; for here is compaſſing the King's Death made Treaſon, and declared by Overt-act; then levying War is made Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Now,</hi> ſays the Repliant, <hi>nothing can be an Overt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57428:10"/>of the firſt, that does any way concern the latter, which is a</hi> Non ſequitur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1. 'Tis very true, the <hi>Juſtifier</hi> does lay down the Rule, and does thence deduce, That conſpiring to levy War cannot be within the meaning of the Clauſe of <hi>Compaſſing the King's Death</hi> in the Stat. <hi>E.</hi> 3. becauſe levying War is particularly mentioned in the Statute after. 2. The Rule is admitted; but it has, it ſeems, <hi>near fourſcore Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> though, by reaſon of the misfortune of our Author's <hi>being confined to a Sheet, or time being wanting,</hi> he has not obliged his Reader with one of that great number. It would have been much more material for him to have ſhewed, That any of the ſaid Exceptions, or the Reaſon of them, did extend to the Point in Queſtion, than to tire his Reader with a long impertinent Preface, and a tedious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignificant Digreſſion of the King's Prerogative of Peace and War, (which take up two or three Pages). If he had omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe, he needed not to have exceeded the Standard of a <hi>Sheet,</hi> and yet have room enough to have given better and more ſatisfactory Anſwers, if he could. 3. The Conſequence, That conſpiring to levy War is not an Overt-act of the Compaſſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe it belongs to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpecies, is clear from the expreſs words of <hi>Coke</hi> and <hi>Hales;</hi> which ſee in the <hi>Juſtification.</hi> And if the Makers of the Statute had deſigned to conclude Conſpiring, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it would not have coſt them above three words more to have added it to the Clauſe of levying War, where it would have more properly come in, then under the Clauſe of Compaſſing, to which it has no Relation, nor no Man could dream of finding it: The poſitive Opinions of <hi>Coke</hi> and <hi>Hales,</hi> the Authority of a Rule of Law, and the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the motive and end of the Statute, which all make againſt our Author, do juſtly merit ſo great a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement and Reſpect to be paid them, that the Caſe ſhould be admitted to be doubtful; and if it be doubtful, then by the expreſs Direction of the Act, the Judges ought to have ſuſpended their Judgment, till they received the Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Parliament. Our Author refers to the Sheet for ſeveral Inſtances to the purpoſe; I have exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57428:11"/>a great many of them, (at length I was weary) and I'le aſſure him there was not one that warranted the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Caſe; Mr. <hi>H.</hi> has been ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular in anſwering them, that he has ſaved all others the Labour. I do not ſay, but that there has been as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Opinions as this, as in the Caſe of him, who ſaid, <hi>His Son was Heir to the Crown,</hi> meaning a Houſe, that had a Crown for a Sign to it; and of him, <hi>Who wiſhed Stag-horns, and all in</hi> Kings <hi>Belly,</hi> meaning one of that Name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe and the like were in violent corrupt times, adjudged Treaſon; but no man ever defended theſe Reſolutions, or eſteem them to be Law, tho they have the Sanction of the judicial Opinions of their ſide.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. He proceeds and ſays, <hi>The Lord</hi> Cobham<hi>'s Caſe is endeavoured to be anſwered by a wonder, that Sir</hi> Edward Coke, <hi>late Lord Chief Juſtice, and then Sheriff, ſhould differ from Mr. Attorney</hi> Coke; <hi>for we know his Thoughts in Sir</hi> Walter Rawleigh<hi>'s time, and in his Speeches in</hi> Car. 1. <hi>his time, they are as different each from the other, as the times were.</hi> I have now (as I had before) occaſion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove our Author for falſe Recitals; the Juſtifiers never ſaid, nor wondered, that my Lord <hi>Coke</hi>'s Opinion was different at one time, from what it was at another; and he was ſo far from ſaying, that his Opinion was different when he was Attorney, from his Opinion in his third In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, (which our Author means) that he believed there was no ſuch Reſolution, as was pretended in the Lord <hi>Cobham</hi>'s Caſe, becauſe my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> did not take notice of it in his Inſt where he taught a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine quite contrary; and alſo, becauſe <hi>Hales</hi> gives ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Account of the Offence of the Lord <hi>Cobham,</hi> than was alledged in my Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Tryal, by the Kings Council. 2. I am as free to Reproach my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> for his Carriage againſt Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> as I am the late King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second Council, for theirs againſt my Lord <hi>Ruſſel;</hi> but for his Speeches in <hi>Car.</hi> 1. his time,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57428:11"/>if he means theſe delivered in Parliament; as many as I have read of them, are very Honeſt, and denote a Zeal and Affection to the Laws and Liberties of his Countrey, and do not in the leaſt derogate from the juſt and ancient Prerogatives of the Crown. 3. Upon the whole, there is nothing material here anſwered to the Objections made by the Juſtifier againſt the Authority of the Lord <hi>Cobham</hi>'s Caſe, quoted in the Tryal, as will appear by comparing this anſwer with the Juſtification; nor is there any thing ſaid to my Lord <hi>Hales</hi> ſtating <hi>Cobham</hi>'s Crime different from the Tryal, from whence we may conclude it was more than a bare Conſpiracy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">XII. He ſays, <hi>Sir</hi> Henry Vane<hi>'s Caſe is endeavoured to be anſwered by this, that</hi> Syderfin <hi>mentions not the Overt-Act in the Indictment, but he does ſay the Treaſon alledged, was a compaſſing the Kings Death; and every Man knows what Sir</hi> Henry Vane <hi>did to accompliſh that; he neither Signed the Warrant to Execute that Murder, nor was he actually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it; The Juſtifier ſays, He does not remember it printed any where, but in</hi> Syderfin<hi>'s Reports; for the refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Memory, I'le tell him of another Book, where it is, and that is</hi> Keeble<hi>'s Reports</hi> 1 Vol. 304. <hi>and there the Indictment is ſaid to be, for compaſſing the Kings Death, and endeavouring to accompliſh the Treaſon, by Changing and Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Government, and Levying War; which Caſe does di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly overthrow all the Defenders, Juſtifiers, and Repliants Arguments, from the diſtinctneſs or difference of the ſort of Treaſons.</hi> 1. Here is another miſtake, for the Juſtifier does not endeavour to anſwer Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi>'s Caſe, becauſe <hi>Syderfin</hi> mentions not the Overt-Acts; but he does not only endeavour, but does effectually anſwer it, becauſe there was other Matters proved againſt him, that did amount to a good Overt-act; and tho he did not Sign the Warrant to Execute that Murder, yet he was concerned in Deſigns for incompaſſing his Civil Death, which is within the Act, as well as his Natural. 2. The Devil owed our Author a ſhame, when he prompt him to refer us to <hi>Keeble;</hi> for by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57428:12"/>that Book, it expreſly appears, that the Changing and Uſurping the Government, was part of Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi>'s Charge, as well as Levying War, which does neceſſarily imply the Kings Depoſition, which no man ever doubted, but was Treaſon; but, how comes this to be applicable to my Lord <hi>R</hi>'s Caſe? 3. This Caſe is ſo far from over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing all the Defenders, Juſtifiers, and Repliants Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, from the diſtinctneſs of the Treaſon, that 'tis plainly conſiſtent with them, and all other Arguments they uſe.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. <hi>Then for Doctor</hi> Story<hi>'s Caſe, 'tis hard to juſtify it for Law, whereas there are above forty places, where it is cited, and agreed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>if any thing be Law, that is ſo, and not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhable from the Caſe in queſtion; but that the Evidence was different, which the Juſtifier would make a reaſon to invalidate this Indictment; the Logick of it paſſeth all underſtanding,</hi> &amp;c. 1. I do ſay, 'Tis hard to juſtify Doctor <hi>Story</hi>'s Caſe accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſummary and imperfect Report of it in <hi>Dyer;</hi> but take it with all the Circumſtances, it is Treaſon; and is nothing like my Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Caſe, who was never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be guilty of adhering to a Foreign Enemy, nor a deſign of Depoſing the King, as in truth <hi>Story</hi> was. 2. I deſire our Author to reconcile his ſaying here, That the Juſtifier would invalidate the Indictment with what he ſaid before, that the Juſtifier admitted the Indictment to be good, and only quarrelled with the Evidence; but Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions and Incongruities, are ſmall Faults. 3. If the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick of diſtinguiſhing my Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Caſe from <hi>Story</hi>'s, becauſe the Evidence againſt them were different, be paſt his underſtanding, I cannot imagine what is within the reach of his Underſtanding; for 'tis clear, that the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is the principal and moſt eſſential Thing to be weighed and conſidered: 'Tis true, our Author has ſaid, That the Evidence was not his Province, but that his Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was to defend the Court and Council. I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy delivered my Thoughts upon that Expreſſion, and ſhall now further ask our Author one Queſtion concerning it;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57428:12"/>whether, if the Evidence was ſhort, and did not warrant the Indictment, it was not the duty of the Court to tell the Jury ſo much, and that therefore they ought to have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted the Priſoner? By his Doctrine, if any Man be Indicted of compaſſing Death of the King, and the Evidence be croſſing a Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er in a pair of Oars, the Court is not to trouble it ſelf about the Evidence, nor to inſtruct the Jury of the inſufficiency of it; and if the Party be Convicted, the Court is in no Fault, becauſe the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was as good as againſt the Murderers of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and the Caſes are only diſtinguiſhable by the proof. Now I have been all along under an Error, (and the una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Conſent of the Books have led me to it) that the Jurors were entirely to be determined in Points of Law by the Court, and that the Court was to ſtate the Law, ariſing from the Proofs to the Jury, and that they were only Judges of the Fact.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. <hi>In</hi> 2d Ander. Grant<hi>'s Caſe, 'twas held, That when any Perſon intendeth or contriveth to Levy War for a thing which the Queen by her Law or Juſtice, ought or may do in Government, as Queen; it's not material, whether they intend any hurt to Her Perſon; but if they intend to Levy War againſt the Office and Authority of the Queen, that's enough; and that Reſolution overthrows the Juſtifiers No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that</hi> J. S.<hi>'s deſign was only to defend the Laws; though the</hi> 13 Eliz. <hi>was then in force, it's a good Argument to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that Pretence.</hi> 1. I have not 2d <hi>Ander.</hi> by me; 'tis out of Print, and I can't procure it, tho I've ſent to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Bookſellers. 2. But even as our Author repreſents it, 'tis nothing to his purpoſe, becauſe he was Indicted on the 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> which made a Conſpiracy to Levy War, Treaſon during her Life; and alſo, becauſe his Deſign was againſt the Office and Authority of the Queen, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies her Dethroning or Depoſition: But by the whole Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Evidence againſt my Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> it is plain, he was aſſenting to no Conſultation, Debate or Reſolution, than what was for the ſupport of the Regal Office and Authority,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57428:13"/>if the Preſervation of our Religion, Laws and Government be ſo.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. Our Author refers us <hi>to the Caſe of the Earls of</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex, <hi>&amp;c. before the then High Steward.</hi> In that Caſe, there was an actual ſorce, and levying War, and therefore not applicable to the Caſe in queſtion; for their Offence was ſpecified in the Stat. <hi>E.</hi> 3. which my Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi> is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. In page 6. Our Author, under the pretence of juſtifying the Guards, makes a long impertinent Excurſion, and maintains <hi>the King's Prerogative of Peace and War, and challenges any body to ſhew the time that there were no armed men in</hi> England; <hi>and expounds the meaning of the Parliament, that they did not deſign the Guards in their Inſtrument of Grievances.</hi> 1. No man queſtions the King's Prerogative of Peace and War; and the Author muſt own himſelf impertinent to talk of it here, unleſs he will juſtify this Conſequence, That if the King can declare War, <hi>&amp;c. then</hi> he may keep ſtanding Guards in times of Peace. 2. It is as little to the purpoſe, though <hi>England</hi> was never without Armed Men; for we know there were ſeveral Caſtles, Gariſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> kept up, and maintained as neceſſary for the defence of the Realm againſt Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Enemies; but I challenge him to ſhew me where any Kings in times of peace were allowed to keep, and quarter Soldiers upon the Subjects, until King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's time. 3. I deſire to know whether the Guards were not part of King <hi>James's Army?</hi> and whether they were not <hi>quartered contrary to Law?</hi> and if ſo, then, I'm fure, they muſt be included in the <hi>Inſtrument of Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances,</hi> as well as any other part of the Army. But he takes no notice of what the Juſtifier ſaid, That they were on great debate voted illegal by the Houſe of Commons in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Long Parliament, of whoſe zeal to the Prerogative no man ever doubted.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57428:13"/>Nor did he conſider that time was, when Judges and others were impeached for perſuading the King to give Liveries to great and unuſual numbers of men to attend him, which were no other than Guards. (<hi>Temp.</hi> Rich. <hi>II.</hi>) That one Article of Male-adminiſtration againſt that King himſelf, was grounded upon his Armed Multitude of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire men.</hi> That even in the times of the War betwixt <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> when the Title to the Crown was ſo tickliſh; yet Standing Armies were not endured then. That King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, having occaſion to raiſe ſome Forces, was limited by Act of Parliament to the Number of Twelve Thouſand. That our later Acts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Martial Law, and quartering of Soldiers upon Perſons againſt their Will, preſuppoſe all Standing Forces in times of Peace to be Illegal: ſince without Marſhal-Law, and Quartering of Soldiers, a Standing Force cannot ſubſiſt. We know of how late ſtanding the very Yeomen of the Guards are: And by an old Act of Parliament we are taught, That <hi>to the King it belongs to prohibit all Force and Arms; And that in order thereunto, His Leiges are bound to Aſſiſt him according to the Laws and Cuſtoms of the Realm</hi> (7 Edw. 1.) But I find no Legal Warrant for our King's raiſing a Force in times of Peace and Quiet, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Conſent of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. I have now conſidered all that our Author hath been pleaſed to anſwer to the Half ſheet called the <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> &amp;c. and do conceive the ſeveral points it undertook to make out, to be vindicated from our Author's Cavils <hi>(viz.)</hi> That the Judgment againſt my Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi> was, 1. Againſt the Authority of the two beſt, and moſt authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Opinions of our Lawyers, <hi>Hales</hi> and <hi>Coke.</hi> 2. Againſt the Opinions of ſeveral Parliaments. 3. Againſt a known Rule and Maxim. 4. And Laſtly, Againſt the end and induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Stat. Ed.</hi> 3. And if this be true, then I ſubmit to any impartial Judgment, whether the Noble Lord might not be ſaid to be Murthered? It is not ſuch a Murther as can be puniſhed in the ordinary courſe and methods of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57428:14"/>Juſtice, becauſe it was committed under the countenance of Law, which I take to be ſo far from leſſening the guilt, that it is an aggravating Circumſtance, <hi>To pervert that Law which is framed and inſtituted for the ſecurity of the Subject, to be a means of his ruine and deſtruction, by undue, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and arbitrary Interpretations of it.</hi> The Original Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlators and Founders of our Government never thought, nor could comprehend, that any Age could arrive to ſuch pitch of wickedneſs, and therefore they provided no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the offence: As the Law of <hi>Rome</hi> had appointed no puniſhment for Parricide, becauſe they believed no Man would be ſo great a Monſter as to be guilty of it. Crimes of ſuch an extraordinary nature, are to receive their condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by the Legiſlative Authority of every Government; and here in <hi>England</hi> it has been very frequent with our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments to enact puniſhments other than were appointed by preceding Laws; or to add to them, when the offence was accompanied with unuſual and aggravating circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; neither can it be pretended that there is any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice in puniſhing by a Law, <hi>ex poſt facto;</hi> any thing that is an offence in it ſelf, and that receives its denomination of evil from an intrinſick quality inherent in it; ſuch as Parricide, which in <hi>Rome</hi> had no puniſhment allotted by the Law; and the barbarous Murders of the Duke of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> in <hi>Calais,</hi> and of the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi>'s Servants by Poiſon, were by ſpecial Statutes declared Treaſon, and the Murtherers of the Duke of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> underwent the common puniſhment of High-Treaſon; and thoſe of the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi>'s Family, were ordered to be Boiled to death; neither of which was the legal puniſhments of their reſpective Crimes: But indeed it would be very unjuſt, at once to make the Offence and to puniſh a perſon who had been guilty of it, when neither the Word of God, the Light of Natural Reaſon, nor any previous municipal Law did warn or inſtruct him of the Tranſgreſſion; ſuch are the Facts of Coyning of Money, Tranſporting of Wooll, and the like, which are very innocent in themſelves, and are unlawful and puniſhable, becauſe they are prohibited
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57428:14"/>as things of a publick damage and detriment. Acts of this kind never were, nor ought to be puniſhed without an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recedent Law to juſtify it. I do not now plead for except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Indemnity any perſons whatſoever; my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is only to ſhew what is juſt and lawful, not what may be expedient for the Parliament to determine againſt ſuch as brought my Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi> and others to an illegal, cruel, and untimely death; and it is our Author's bold affirmation, <hi>That they are as ſafe as under an Indemnity,</hi> that has miniſtred the occaſion of diſcourſing upon this <hi>Topick.</hi> I conſeſs I am very ill inſtructed in the Caſes of the reſt that were hurried to their Graves through the violence of the late times; my remembrance of them is not more perfect, than one may be preſumed to retain from a tranſient and curſory peruſal of their Trials; but by a general conſent of all Lawyers, the Sentence againſt many of them is not more to be defended than that of my Lord <hi>R.</hi> Mr. <hi>Sidney</hi>'s, and Mr. <hi>Hampden</hi>'s, had the ſame weak foundation, only with this difference, That the latter pleaded guilty; but it is plain from what has been already ſaid upon my Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Caſe, that he was not, unleſs he was conſcious of ſome other guilt, than was charged on that Noble Lord. 'Tis true, in all Inferior Juriſdictions and Courts he is eſtop't to ſay he is innocent, and that the Plea was extorted from him through menace of Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Drawing and Quartering, becauſe the admittance of ſuch a Plea is, repugnant to a Rule of Law, <hi>That there can be no averment againſt matter of Record,</hi> and the Plea is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded: but whatever Acts in <hi>pais,</hi> and that are not recorded, a man executes unvoluntarily by dureſs or threat of being beaten, impriſoned, or ſear of other bodily hurt, he may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void them by pleading the ſpecial matter in an Inferior Court; as for the purpoſe, all Bonds, Specialties, Deeds, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If a man conſider this difference abſtracted from the aforeſaid Maxim, it will ſeem very abſurd, and unreaſonable, that one ſhall be allowed to diſannul an Act he perſormed to ſave a beating, or a ſhort Impriſonment (for which the Law would have given him reparation
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57428:15"/>proportionable to the damage he ſhould ſuſtain) and that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſhall not be received to make vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d his Plea, by ſaying, That he was forced to it to ſave himſelf and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily from the ignominy of dying under a Gallows; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Caſes of this nature the Parliament ought to give aid and relief, which may be done without inconvenience; ſince the Parliament (the Seat of the Legiſlative Power) has an unlimited Juriſdiction, and neither is, nor ought to be ſo ſtreightly bound up as Subordinate Courts. From Mr. <hi>Hambden</hi>'s Plea there ought no inference to be made to the prejudice of my Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> ſince it was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther involuntary. Upon the whole, I have peruſed that Noble Lord's Trial with the exacteſt care and curioſity, and I do profeſs I can diſcover no Crime, nor Conſpiracy, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than he was engaged in by an hereditary and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken Zeal and Concernment for the Religion; Laws and Liberties of his Countrey; and yet our Author has the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to repeat in both his Sheets, That his Relations were pleaſed with the Juſtice diſpenced to him by the Court. His Judgment cannot be defended without reflexion on our preſent Government, which is founded on the generous, and ſucceſsful Attempt made by the People of <hi>England,</hi> under the Auſpicious Conduct of His preſent Majeſty, to recover their Ancient Birthrights. 'Tis true, we that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in this Revolution, are juſtified by a greater number of breaches and violations of our Laws. And we have carried our reſentments further. There were Incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſufficient upon the people (as appears before) to authorize whatever he tranſacted; and we found they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and grew at length to ſuch a height, that we were forced to abandon our beloved Doctrine of <hi>Paſſive-Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and <hi>Non-reſiſtance;</hi> for a long time we were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained the uſe of other than the Spiritual-weapons of <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears;</hi> ſo long, that all the Secular and Civil Rights of the Kingdom were deſtroyed: At length thoſe two <hi>Leviathans,</hi> the <hi>Diſpencing Power,</hi> and the <hi>High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion Court</hi> were ſet up, and began to prey upon the <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> of the Church, and then our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:57428:15"/>gave us leave to reſort to other ſort of Arms, which in leſs than ſix weeks time redeemed them and us. For my part, I was bred, and will live and dye in the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as by Law eſtabliſhed. I believe it to be the beſt conſtituted Church in the World both for Doctrine and Diſcipline; and as upon the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation She caſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ered thoſe luxuriant Ceremonies that in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſpread ſo far as to cover and ſhadow the root and ſubſtance of Religion, ſo She ſeems to retain ſew more than are competent and neceſſary for the decent and orderly diſcharge of Divine Service; but my Affection to the Church cannot ſo far blind my Judgment, as to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the conduct of a great many of her Miniſters, and Clergy. I was willing to compound with them, and to admit, That <hi>Fighting their Mothers Battle</hi> with ſo great Courage in her late diſtreſs, ſhould be an expiatory ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to ſhrieve and abſolve them from their former errors and miſcarriages: But I can hardly forgive ſuch as now unſeaſonably return to their Vomit of <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> (which they themſelves, by experience, ſo lately found to be abſurd and inconſiſtent with the general Laws of Nature and Self-preſervation) and that endeavour by their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (as much as in them lye) to alienate the bearts of the people from the Government, at a conjuncture, when the common danger of Religion and Laws do abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the cloſeſt union, and the ſtrongeſt and moſt entire coallition of all the Proteſtants Power and Intereſt. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not frame any colourable excuſe or apology for theſe ſort of Men. Their Murmurings and Diſcontents cannot proceed from the influence of their ancient and exploded Principle; for even thoſe ſteps towards the late Change which they encouraged, authorized, or concurred in, were as much a departure from, and a contradiction to the notion of <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> as the <hi>Abdication</hi> it ſelf: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I allow that they can be the reſult of juſt and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional fears of a deſign to turn this well tempered Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy into a Republick; ſince that is more effectually obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated and prevented by ſetling Their Majeſties upon the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57428:16"/>Throne, than it would have been by the <hi>Regency,</hi> or any other project that has been propounded or diſcourſed of; nay, I had almoſt ſaid, That the Regency did change our Monarchy into a Commonwealth; for it ſtript King <hi>James</hi> of all his <hi>Prerogatives</hi> and <hi>Powers;</hi> it left him indeed the Title of a King, but the adminiſtration of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was to be lodged and intruſted in other hands. <hi>Sparta</hi> had an Officer that bore the ſtyle of King; but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that, the Government of <hi>Sparta</hi> is tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us under the Title of a <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> for in truth, the King had not theſe Juriſdictions nor Franchiſes, in which the Eſſence of <hi>Monarchy</hi> conſiſts. Such a King as there was (of old) in <hi>Sparta,</hi> would the Project of the Regency have made King <hi>James;</hi> which really was no more than to ſet him up as a <hi>Pageant of State,</hi> and a Statue of Authority: But by ſetling the Crown upon Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties, it is preſerved in its true, rightful and ancient Luſtre, Powers and Prerogatives. 'Tis true, The Rules of the Hereditary Succeſſion are, and muſt have been broke when King <hi>James</hi> was laid aſide, and no perſon whatſoever could, during his Life, be exalted to the Throne under that Qualification; for <hi>non eſt baeres viventis, a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Man can have no Heir,</hi> is a Maxim of our Laws. Since therefore all thoughts of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reſtitution were abandoned, and that no perſon could of right lay claim to the Crown, it would have been next degree to madneſs, to appoint any perſon for King, that was not in a capacity to diſcharge the Duty and Office of a King, which is to defend and protect his People. Such a Power I do conceive to be a more eſſential Qualification and Property of a Sovereign Prince, than any Right or Title by Deſcent or Proximity of Blood; for <hi>that</hi> is required by the Fundamental Maxims of Government in general; <hi>this</hi> only by Municipal Laws and Sanctions. So that if a People ſet up for their Supream Governor one that wants ſome Legal Qualifications, the worſt imputation that <hi>malice</hi> can fix upon them, is, that they do tranſgreſs againſt the Laws of their Country; but, if they let up one for their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57428:16"/>Governor that is not able to <hi>protect</hi> them, they do certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offend againſt the firſt and original End of all Political Conſtitutions, which is the Publick Peace and Safety: and how far the Municipal Laws of any particular Kingdom or State do retain their force, when they come to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere with the Superior Laws of Nature and Self-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and with the Ends of Government in general, I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to every man's conſideration. What our Anceſtors here in <hi>England</hi> thought of this Matter, may be eaſily col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from the great number they had of Kings <hi>de facto,</hi> that were not ſo <hi>de jure;</hi> and as no man that is verſed in our Hiſtories can be ignorant of this, ſo no man that is any thing acquainted with with our Laws, but muſt know they make no difference (in point of Allegiance) between a King <hi>de facto</hi> and <hi>de jure.</hi> Whatever is High-Treaſon againſt the one, is againſt the other; nay, our Books car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry this matter higher, and do teach us, That the levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing War under the Authority of a King <hi>de jure</hi> againſt him that is King <hi>de facto,</hi> is ſuch an indelible Character of a Traytor, that he may be tried and condemned in the Reign of ſuch King <hi>de jure,</hi> if ever he happens to be a King <hi>de facto</hi> likewiſe.</p>
            <p>As His preſent Majeſty was the only Perſon able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore to us our Religion, and our Ancient Government; ſo it was on Him alone we could have depended for the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of theſe Bleſſings. When I reflect upon the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Diſpoſition of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army after the <hi>Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> upon the Powers and Strength of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and upon the uncertainty of <hi>Scotland,</hi> I do not ſee how it was poſſible for us to have ſupported our ſelves, if the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had withdrawn himſelf, and his Troops, from among us, and left us to ſhift for our ſelves, as undoubtedly he would, and ought to have done, if we had excluded him from any ſhare in the <hi>Regal Office;</hi> for every body knows he made ſuch a Figure in the Government of the States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the United Provinces; as rendred him one of the greateſt and moſt conſiderable Princes of Chriſtendom; and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57428:17"/>was it reaſonable to expect he ſhould have relinquiſhed his Poſt in his Native Countrey, and be content to live among us in the quality of a Subject? Was it reaſonable that he ſhould expoſe his Life, his Fortune, and all that was dear to him, to reſcue us from that State of Thraldom and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, that we and our Poſterities ſeemed to have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to; and ſhould we make ſo ungrateful a return on our parts, as to place him in a meaner Degree, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a more private Condition of life, than he was before he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwent ſuch hazards, and ſuſtained ſuch Difficulties for our ſakes? Certainly the diſſatisfaction ſome People expreſs at our preſent Eſtabliſhment, muſt be occaſioned for want of a due and ſerious conſideration of that <hi>Deliverance</hi> which Providence has made our King the Inſtrument of. If any man maturely reflects upon the preceding and concurring Accidents and Emergencies of the late aſtoniſhing <hi>Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> he muſt admit, that God Almighty did in an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and particular manner direct, conduct and approve the Riſe, Progreſs and Concluſion of it.</p>
            <p>To conclude, The ſetting the Character of my Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi> in its true and deſerved Light; the redeeming his Name and Memory from the ſtain and infamy of the higheſt Crimes; the proving his Childrens Title to the greateſt degree of Honor and Vertue on the part of their Father (which by the Univerſal conſent of all they will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive and inherit from their Mother,) and reſtoring to the Laws and Juſtice of <hi>England</hi> their primitive Credit and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, are the ſole abſtracted Motives which prompted me to this undertaking. I have not left the leaſt <hi>handle</hi> for malice or ill nature to ſuſpect, that what has been here ſaid in relation to the Government, or my Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> is the reſult of any external hope of advantage or preferment, or of a ſervile diſpoſition to flatter ſuch as are in Power. My Reſolution not to be known, will both ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure me againſt thoſe Imputations, and againſt that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, which is the reward of ill Writers.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:57428:17"/>
            <p>I do not pretend to be of ſo moroſe, nor <hi>Stoical</hi> a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as to think that at all times, and upon all occaſions, men ſhould confine themſelves to ſpeak or write nothing but what is the true and real Dictates of their Judgments. The extravagant ſtrains of Flattery which <hi>Pliny</hi> beſtows upon the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors in his Panegyricks, was no hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to his living and dying with the reputation of a very honeſt and ſincere Perſon: To magnify the Power of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and the other Heathen Gods, in a Declaration or Poem, was never eſteemed Blaſphemy againſt the Great <hi>Jehovah:</hi> And if a man be to ſpeak or write to his Miſtreſs, 'twill be ill manners to tell her that he courts her for her Fortune, though it be the truth. I do not cenſure the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity Orator (who, I've heard, did in his Speech to <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, highly commend him for his Sincerity, Singleneſs of Heart, and his exact obſervation-of his Word and Promiſes) for any other thing than this, That he ſhould have praiſed him for ſome other Vertues, than thoſe he was ſo univerſally known never to have practiſed. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Occaſions 'tis expected men ſhould exert their Wit and Fancy, not their Veracity; and I cannot deny, That to make truth on theſe Occaſions the ſtandard, may be clowniſhneſs and ill-breeding. But, I'm ſure, I would as ſoon cut off my Right Hand, as ſuffer it to write any thing that is not the reſult of my ſober and deliberate Thoughts and Judgment upon ſo ſerious, weighty and ſolemn a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject as I have here preſumed to diſcourſe upon.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:57428:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Richard Baldwin.</head>
            <p>THE Hiſtory of the Moſt Illuſtrious <hi>William,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange:</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd from the firſt Founders of the Ancient Houſe of <hi>Naſſau:</hi> Together with the moſt conſiderable Actions of this preſent Prince. <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Fourteen Papers, Relating to the Affairs of Church and State, in the Reign of the late King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Character of a Trimmer. His Opinion of I. The Laws and Government. II. Proteſtant Religion. III. The Papiſts. IV. Foreign Affairs. By the Honourable Sir <hi>W. Coventry.</hi> The Third Edition, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Corrected, and cleared from the Errors of the firſt Impreſſion.</p>
            <p>An Impartial Relation of the Illegal Proceedings againſt St. <hi>Mary Magdal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> College in <hi>Oxon,</hi> in the Year of our Lord 1687. Containing only Matters of Fact as they occurred. <hi>The Second Edition.</hi> To which is added the moſt Remarkable Paſſages, omitted in the former, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Severity of the Preſs. Collected by a Fellow of the ſaid Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege.</p>
            <p>The Abſolute Neceſſity of ſtanding vigorouſly by the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: Or, A view of what both Church-men and Diſſenters muſt expect, if by their unhappy Diviſions, Popery and Tyranny ſhould return again.</p>
            <p>A Defence of the Late Lord <hi>Ruſſells</hi> Innocency, By way of Anſwer or Confutation of a Libellous Pamphlet, Entituled, <hi>An Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Poyſon:</hi> With Two Letters of the Author of this Book, upon the Subject of his Lordſhip's Tryal.</p>
            <p>Together with an Argument in the Great Caſe concerning Elections of Members to Parliament, between Sir <hi>Samuel Barnardiſton,</hi> Plaintiff, and Sir <hi>William Soames,</hi> Sheriff of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> Defendant, In the Court of <hi>King's Bench,</hi> in an Action upon the Caſe, and afterwards by Error ſued in the Exchequer-Chamber.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Innocency further defended; by way of Reply to an Anſwer, Entituled, <hi>The Magiſtracy and Government of</hi> England <hi>Vindicated.</hi> Both writ by Sir <hi>Robert Atkyns,</hi> Knight of the Honourable Order of the <hi>Bath,</hi> and now Lord Chief Baron of His Majeſty's Court of <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
